Guide to the Mason Fitch Cogswell Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mason Fitch Cogswell papers
1772-1853
1790-1830
GEN MSS 920
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.59
(5 boxes)
The papers primarily consist of correspondence received by Mason Fitch Cogswell from family, friends, and professional colleagues. Prominent among the correspondents are Cogswell's brother Samuel Cogswell, his nephew James Lloyd Cogswell of Long Island, New York, his friend Theodore Dwight, the Caribbean planter Charles Joseph Sibert, Vicomte de Cornillon, and deaf education pioneers Laurent Clerc and T. H. Gallaudet. Other colleagues in the papers are the Reverend Ebenezer Fitch, Connecticut congressman John Davenport, inventor Apollos Kinsley, and a number of American physicians including Oliver Fisk of Worcester, Henry Fish and E. H. Smith of New York, and Joseph Strong of Philadelphia. Notably, there are several letters from Cogswell's many female friends such as Nancy Roy Fox and Delia Dwight Porter. Also in the correspondence is a fair copy of a letter to Cogswell's father James Cogswell from British author William Cowper. Other papers include two diaries kept by Cogswell in 1788 and 1791, financial and legal papers, and a group of manuscript medical remedies and treatments.
Cogswell, Mason Fitch, 1761-1830
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Grace Cogswell Root, 1925 and 1926. One diary was the gift of the Misses Tully, 1896.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Mason Fitch Cogswell's 1788 diary is available on microfilm (MS Vault film 1713)
Cogswell Family Tree
Family members whose letters are prominent in the collection are underlined.
Rev. James Cogswell (1720-1807)
m1 1745 Alice Fitch (1725-1772)
m2 Martha Lothrop Devotion (1715?-1795)
m3 Irene Ripley Hibbard (d. 1804)
- -1 James Cogswell (1746-1792) m 1776 Elizabeth Davenport (1756-1779); m 1783 Abigail Lloyd (1751-1830)
- -- -2 Alice Cogswell (1777-1850) m. 1805 Samuel Fisher (1777-1856)
- -- -2 James Lloyd Cogswell (1784-1831) m 1819 Sarah Burr Sherwood (1788-1830)
- -- -- -3 Sarah B. Cogswell (1820-1875)
- -- -- -3 James A. Cogswell (1822-1837)
- -- -- -3 Mary Ledyard Cogswell (1824-1841)
- -- -2 John Lloyd Cogswell (1789-1831) m 1821 Love B. Coffin (1795-1857)
- -- -- -3 John T. (1823-1866),
- -- -- -3 Charlotte Broome Cogswell (b. 1825),
- -- -- -3 Samuel F. Cogswell (1827-1858)
- -- -- -3 Alice Fisher Cogswell (b. 1829)
- -- -- -3 Mason Fitch Cogswell (1830-1832)
- -- -2 Sarah Lloyd Cogswell (1786-1848)
- -- -2 Harriet Broome Cogswell (1790-1843) m 1819 Robert Willis Mott (1796-1846)
- -- -- -3 Harriet Stella Mott (1820-1902?) m 1843 William Handy Onderdonk (1820-1882)
- -1 Alice Cogswell (1749-1772)
- -1 Samuel Cogswell (1754-1790) m 1785 Maria Backus (1767-1834); she m 1792 Ebenezer Fitch (1756-1833)
- -- -2 Mason Backus Cogswell (1787-1790)
- -- -2 James Fitch Cogswell (1789-1862)
- -- -2 Maria Cogswell (1790-1870) m 1810 Douglas W. Sloane
- -1 MASON FITCH COGSWELL (1761-1830) m. Mary Austin Ledyard
- -- -2 Mary Austin Cogswell (1801-1868) m 1828 Lewis Weld (1796-1858)
- -- -- -3 Mason Cogswell Weld (1829-1887) m 1866 Martha M. Coles
- -- -- -3 Charles Theodore Weld (1831-1863)
- -- -- -3 Lewis Ledyard Weld (1833-1865)
- -- -- -3 Mary Elizabeth Weld (b. 1835)
- -- -- -3 Alice Cogswell Weld (b. 1837) m 1871 William H. Hodge
- -- -2 Elizabeth Cogswell (1803-1856) m 1831 John Treadwell Norton (1795-1869)
- -- -2 Alice Cogswell (1805-1830)
- -- -2 Mason Fitch Cogswell (1809-1865) m 1847 Lydia Bradford
- -- -2 Catharine Ledyard Cogswell (1811-1882) m. 1836 Cortlandt Van Rensselaer
- -1 Septimus Cogswell (1769-1773)
Mason Fitch Cogswell (1761-1830)
Mason Fitch Cogswell, an American physician and surgeon, was born on September 28, 1761, in Canterbury, Connecticut, the third son of the Reverend James and Alice Fitch Cogswell. An 1780 graduate of Yale College, he studied medicine with his brother James Cogswell, first in Stamford, Connecticut, and later in New York City. In 1789, Cogswell established a medical office in Hartford, where he practiced until his death in 1830.
Cogswell and his wife Mary Austin Ledyard Cogswell had five children including their daughter Alice, who became deaf as a child. In an effort to educate her and other deaf residents of the state, Cogswell enlisted the aid of Laurent Clerc and Thomas H. Gallaudet to establish in 1817 in Hartford the Connecticut Asylum for the Education and Instruction of Deaf and Dumb Persons, now the American School for the Deaf, the country's first permanent school for the deaf.
Scope and Contents
The papers primarily consist of correspondence received by Mason Fitch Cogswell from family, friends, and professional colleagues. Prominent among the correspondents are Cogswell's brother Samuel Cogswell, his nephew James Lloyd Cogswell of Long Island, New York, his friend Theodore Dwight, the Caribbean planter Charles Joseph Sibert, Vicomte de Cornillon, and deaf education pioneers Laurent Clerc and T. H. Gallaudet. Other colleagues in the papers are Reverend Ebenezer Fitch, Connecticut congressman John Davenport, inventor Apollos Kinsley, and a number of American physicians including Oliver Fisk of Worcester, Henry Fish and E. H. Smith of New York, and Joseph Strong of Philadelphia. Notably, there are several letters from Cogswell's many female friends such as Nancy Roy Fox and Delia Dwight Porter. Also in the correspondence is a fair copy of a letter to Cogswell's father James Cogswell from British author William Cowper. Other papers include two diaries kept by Cogswell in 1788 and 1791, financial and legal papers, and a group of manuscript medical remedies and treatments. Accompanying the papers are a group of printed items.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1772-1830. II. Writings, 1788-1853. III. Other Papers, 1783-1830.
Deaf -- Education -- Connecticut; Medicine -- Practice -- United States; Physicians -- Connecticut; Physicians -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Physicians -- New York (State); Diaries -- Connecticut -- 18th century; Prescriptions -- United States -- 18th century; Prescriptions -- United States -- 19th century; Subscription lists (Publishing) -- Connecticut -- Norwich -- 1793; Physicians -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- 18th century; Physicians -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- 19th century; Breed, Shub. (Shubael), 1759-1840; Clerc, Laurent, 1785-1869; Cogswell, James, 1720-1807; Cogswell, James, 1746-1792; Cogswell, Mary Ledyard; Cogswell, Mason Fitch, 1761-1830; Cogswell, Samuel, 1754-1790; Cowper, William, 1731-1800; Davenport, John, 1752-1830; Doolittle, Mark, 1781-1855; Dwight, Nathaniel, 1770-1831; Dwight, Theodore, 1764-1846; Fish, Henry; Fisk, Oliver; Fitch, Ebenezer, 1756-1833; Fox, Nancy Roy; Gallaudet, T. H. (Thomas Hopkins), 1787-1851; Goddard, Calvin, 1768-1842; Kinsley, Apollos; Martel, Michael; Morgan, Titus, 1776-1811; Porter, Fedelia Dwight, 1708-1847; Smith, E. H. (Elihu Hubbard), 1771-1798; Storrs, Seth, 1756-1837; Strong, Joseph, 1770-1812; Academy of Medicine of Philadelphia; Bushnell & Hubbard; Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences; Society of Brothers in Unity (Yale College)
- Correspondence, 1772-1830; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Family, and Colleagues and Friends.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I primarily contains letters sent to Cogswell by his family, medical colleagues in several cities and towns, and a variety of friends. The first subseries, family correspondence, holds more than thirty letters from Cogswell to his father James, and over fifty letters from Cogswell's younger brother Samuel, who died tragically at age 36; also in the subseries are letters from the Reverend Ebenezer Fitch, a cousin who married Samuel's widow Maria and raised their three children. Also in the subseries is a fair copy of a letter to James Cogswell from the British author William Cowper.
  The second subseries holds letters from Cogswell's friends and peers. Notable among them is his friend Theodore Dwight, a lawyer and publisher, who signed his letters "Orlando," and Charles Joseph Sibert, Vicomte de Cornillon, a planter from Santo Domingo. When letters from Cogswell are present, they are noted at the folder level; at the end of the series is a folder holding copies of other outgoing letters.
  - Family
    - Cogswell, Abigail Lloyd, 1792-1812 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cogswell, James (father)
      - Letters from and to Mason Fitch Cogswell, 1781-1795 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Letter to James Cogswell from William Cowper (fair copy), 1791 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Letter to James Cogswell from J. Huntington, 1772, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cogswell, James (brother), 1791-1792 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cogswell, James Fitch, 1815-1816 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cogswell, James Lloyd, 1810-1830 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cogswell, John Lloyd, 1811, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cogswell, Mary Austin Ledyard
      - Letters to and from Mason Fitch Cogswell (husband), 1809-1816 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Letter from Mason Fitch Cogswell (son), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Cogswell, Samuel
      - Letters to Mason Fitch Cogswell, 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
      - Letter to James and Martha Cogswell, 1790 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        General note
        Concerning the death of his son Mason Backus Cogswell
    - Fisher, Alice, 1809, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Fisher, Samuel, 1816-1820 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Fitch, Ebenezer, 1798-1816 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lloyd, Henry, 1789-1818 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lloyd, John, 1789-1792 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Mott, Robert W., and Harriet B. Cogswell, 1808-1820 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Weld, Lewis, and Mary Austin Cogswell, 1812-1830 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Includes letters from Mason Fitch Cogswell
  - Colleagues and Friends
    - A general, 1792-1823 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - B general, 1784-1826 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Barker, Jonathan, 1793-1794 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Boardman, Timothy, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Breed, Betsey, 1793-1794 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Breed, Shub, 1784-1787 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Broome, 1784-1790 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Brown, 1793-1823 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Butler, 1820-1822 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - C general, 1785-1827 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Capers, 1787-1795 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Clark, Thaddeus, 1797-1822 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Clerc, Laurent, 1817, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Cotton, James Watson, 1816-1820 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - D general, 1790-1821 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Davenport, John, 1800-1816 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Doolittle, Mark, 1819-1821 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Dwight, Nathaniel, 1792-1824 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Dwight, Theodore, 1785-1830 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
      Includes one letter from Lewis Burr Sturges to Dwight
    - E general, 1799-1817 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - F general, 1790-1828 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Farrell, Nicholas, 1789, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Field, Simeon, 1814-1818 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Finley, James Edward Burr, 1784-1787 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Finley, Samuel, 1785-1788 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Fish, Henry, 1811-1815 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Fisk, Oliver, 1810-1811 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Includes a letter from Mason Fitch Cogswell
    - Fitch, 1784-1830 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Fox, Nancy Roy, 1782-1790, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - G general, 1790-1829 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Gallaudet, T. H. (Thomas Hopkins), 1816-1830 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Includes two letters to Lewis Weld
    - Goddard, Calvin, 1812-1827 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - H general, 1785-1830 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Howe, 1813-1822 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Hubbard, Thomas, 1811-1818 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Hunt, 1796-1810 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - J general, 1799-1819 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - K general, 1812-1822 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Kinsley, Apollos, 1791-1800 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - L general, 1792-1822 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Lee, 1792-1824 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - M general, 1789-1825 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Mead, 1793-1821 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Morgan, Titus, 1803-1806 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Moore, Eliza, 1787-1788, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Moore, Mary Ann, 1787-1788 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - N general, 1816 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Osborn, John, 1795 Oct 14 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - P general, 1789-1821 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Pattin, William, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Porter, Delia Dwight, 1785-1791, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - R general, 1807-1829 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Rhodes, Dudley W., 1814-1818 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - S general, 1792-1822 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Sanford, Clark, 1810-1811 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Seymour, James S., 1821-1828 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Sibert Cornillon, Charles Joseph, vicomte de, 1792-1794 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, 1812 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Smith, 1789-1815 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Smith, E. H. (Elihu Hubbard), 1790-1798 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Storrs, Seth, 1785-1788 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Strong, Joseph, 1792-1801 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - T general, 1795-1830 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Utley, Vine, 1817 Sep 26 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - V general, 1797-1816 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Vandevoort, Deborah, 1792-1794, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - W general, 1793-1830 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Welles, Benjamin, 1784-1788 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Welles, Rebecca, 1783-1786 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Wetmore, Prosper, 1790 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Wilcox, Samuel, 1787-1788 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Woolsey, 1788-1790 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Yale College, 1828, 1830 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Unidentified, 1786-1790, undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Copies of outgoing letters, 1795-1821 (Box 3, Folder 97)
- Writings, 1788-1791, 1853; Series II; 4
  The series contains two autograph manuscript diaries kept by Mason Fitch Cogswell, including one written during a trip from Hartford to New York, returning to Stamford, Connecticut. Also present are a variety of writings in various hands, some likely by Cogswell. The latest item in the Cogswell papers is filed here, a transcript of a song sung at a Yale College event in 1853 by the Class of 1854; this item was owned by Cogswell's grandson Lewis Ledyard Weld. The donors of second diary were likely the daughters of Dr. William Tully, who had studied medicine under Cogswell.
  - Diary, November 14-December 20, 1788, with a later transcription by Mary Ledyard Cogswell, 1788, undated (Box 4, Folder 98)
    The provenance of this diary is discussed in The Cogswells in America, by E. O. Jameson (1884), pages 245-46.
  - Diary, January 31-February 22, 1791 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of the Misses Tully, 1896.
  - Poems, undated (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Epitaphs and miscellaneous notes, 1853, undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
- Other Papers, 1783-1830; Series III; 5
  The series holds financial, legal, and medical papers, including remedies and treatments for cancer and other diseases collected by Cogswell. Two folders at the end of the series hold printed documents including two copies of a 1793 printed form issued by Norwich, Connecticut, publisher Bushnell & Hubbard, seeking subscribers for two proposed books by Michael Martel, The French Scholar's Diversion, and Martel's Virgil. The forms were signed by several residents of Hartford, New London, and other towns in Connecticut, but the volumes were never published.
  - Financial papers, 1789-1830 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Legal papers, 1783-1829 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Medical papers, 1787, undated (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Printed material
    - Forms, circular letters, and broadside, 1800-1817 (Box 4, Folder 105)
      Includes Constitution of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences (1800); membership letter from Academy of Medicine of Philadelphia, signed by Philip Syng Physick (1800); report of the Boston Medical Society (1810); and Scheme of the Exercises at the Exhibition of the Brothers' Society, Yale College (December 31, 1817)
    - Subscription forms for Michael Martel publications, 1793 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 106)